<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A newe reuenge for an olde grudge. Lately sette forth by I.S. VVho buildeth not vpon sure grounde, hath often beene, and now is founde a losse of time, a vaine expence, thus saith Goddes worde. An ouerthrowe of his presence. Thankes to the Lorde</title>
            <author>Sutton, J., fl. 1567-1573.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1567</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 22 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13201</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23498</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101971</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837774</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837774</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2116</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13201)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2116)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1035:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A newe reuenge for an olde grudge. Lately sette forth by I.S. VVho buildeth not vpon sure grounde, hath often beene, and now is founde a losse of time, a vaine expence, thus saith Goddes worde. An ouerthrowe of his presence. Thankes to the Lorde</title>
                  <author>Sutton, J., fl. 1567-1573.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Henry Wylkes, for Francis Coldocke[,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1567]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>I.S. = J. Sutton.</note>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Anti-Catholic pamphlet; supports Bishop Jewel and opposes Thomas Harding in Church of England controversy.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A B⁶.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Lambeth Palace Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jewel, John, 1522-1571 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Harding, Thomas, 1516-1572 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2116:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2116:1"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A NEWE Reuenge for an olde Grudge.</p>
            <p>Lately ſette foorth by I. S.</p>
            <q>
               <l>VVho buildeth not vpon ſure grounde,</l>
               <l>hath often beene, and now is founde</l>
               <l>A loſſe of time, a vaine expence,</l>
               <l>Thus ſaith Goddes worde.</l>
               <l>An ouerthrowe of his pretence.</l>
               <l>Thankes to the Lorde.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Jmprinted at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don by Henry Wykes, for Frances Coldocke.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:2116:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2116:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or aſmuche as we are taught in the firſte of <hi>Ioſua,</hi> that in the booke of <hi>God</hi> we ſhould recorde day and night: and alſo be circumſpecte to doo accordyng to the ſame, that our wayes might proſper: ſo aſſuredly, they that in that ſort trauell, and make ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of a willinge exerciſe, ſhall finde therin ſuch Felicitie, ſuch fruitefulnes, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte,
<pb facs="tcp:2116:3"/> as I (oh Chriſtian Reader) am not with my penne able to expreſſe: for in the Scriptures is wealth to be founde for thoſe that be in miſerie: helth for ſuch as be ſicke: lighte to expell darkeneſſe: comfort to thoſe that be afflicted: in extreme perill, preſent preſeruation: and for the defence and ſauegarde of ſuche as are of the houſeholde of Faithe, there is alſo to be fownde
<pb facs="tcp:2116:3"/> both armour and weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to wage battel with that aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t enemie Satan: of whom as the ſacred <hi>Scriptures</hi> make mention, to haue bene euen from the beginninge an vtter enemie to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> his Goſpell, and profeſſours of the ſame: and ſekinge in ſundrie wiſe through his ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teltie to ſubuert the, whome although the glorious <hi>God</hi> at no time leaueth vndefen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, to the greater co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſion
<pb facs="tcp:2116:4"/> and ſhame of that ſubtile Serpent, yet for al that ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth he not ſtill to ſtirre vp his Helliſh armie, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to make new attemptes to trouble and aſſayle the flocke and famelie of the Faithfull: and that onely as muche as in them is, to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, and darken the light of the glorious Goſpel of our <hi>Sauiour Ieſus Chriſte,</hi> which comfortablie ſhineth amongst vs, which through
<pb facs="tcp:2116:4"/> Chriſte wee haue receiued, whiche we now enioye, and are partakers of (to God be tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes therfore) who grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the ſame a free paſſage tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the whole worlde, to the more magnifiynge of his mightie name, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuall comforte of his Church, and vtter deſtruction of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and aduerſaries of the ſame, For euer. Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:2116:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2116:5"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A newe Reuenge for an olde Grudge.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Monge the diuers &amp; ſundrie conflictes betweene Chriſte &amp; Sata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: the Churche Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church Diaboliall; the Churche of Chriſte, and the Churche of Antichriſt (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Scriptures plentifully make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> by many examples; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and at all times when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> happened, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, when God hath ſuffred them to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of his Churche, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, as alſo for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> his glory) there hath
<pb facs="tcp:2116:6"/> not then, I ſay, wanted among an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable ſorte of deadly enemies, one Satanicall ſouldiour, whiche hath euer ſhewed him ſelfe more ſtouter then others: more wickedly bent then the reſt: more puffed vp in pryde: more deſirous by defacinge the truth, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunce Sinne: boulder, in the behalfe of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Satan, and to thunder out threatninges againſt Chriſte and his Congregation, whiche examples <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Scriptures <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> many; as of <hi>Herode, Phara<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> more: amongſt the whiche I ſpecially note the great <hi>Golliah,</hi> that preſumptuouſe <hi>Philiſtine,</hi> who ſo proudely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> him ſelfe againſt the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> accordyng to the Scriptures <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, his Helmet of braſſe his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> mayle, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of braſſe his ſhielde on his ſhoulder, his ſworde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his ſide, and in his hands a ſpeare of greate waight: and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ayes ſuppoſinge that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of his perſon, the furniture of his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour,
<pb facs="tcp:2116:6"/> and force of his weapons, ſhould be ſuche a terrour to them, as that it ſhoulde vtterly abaſhe and diſcourage the hole Campe to encou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ter with him, did therefore ſhewe and aduaunce him ſelfe before the whole hoſte of the <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites,</hi> makyng there callenge to fight with any one that might be choſen out from amongſt them. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>olde now I praye you, how this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Philiſtine</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>earynge bolde of him ſelfe, and buildynge vpon his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth and deſpiſinge the God of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> was in the twinklinge of an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne in the chiefeſt of his pryde, and that by little <hi>Dauid,</hi> who for the ſmalneſſe of his ſtature, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of his yéeres, <hi>Goliah</hi> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that he ſhoulde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>atche with him, this kynge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> turned vp <hi>Dauids</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> was he much deceyued: for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of a man, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtrength of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> God onely that giueth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:2116:7"/> how weake <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> man ſéeme to be in bodye, yet is he mightie &amp; ſtrong, if the Lorde aſſiſt him, as he did his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt <hi>Dauid:</hi> who puttinge his truſte neyther in ſpeare nor ſhielde, but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng his whole affiance and truſte in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>inge Lorde, who is the geuer of victorie and by whome he was appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Champion in Iſraels behalfe, manlike marched then forward in the name of the Lorde God of Hoſtes to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> enemie, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a Slinge wherein was a ſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>, whiche he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ange at <hi>Golliah,</hi> and there<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> him ſuche a blowe in the forehead, that downe he falleth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> at <hi>Dauids</hi> féete vpon the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:2116:7"/> flie, they haue loſt the fielde, to God be thankes therefore. But beholde now a newe broyle, and accordinge to the ſayinge of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eccleſi. 1.</note> 
               <hi>The thyng that hath bene cometh to paſſe agayne: And the thyng that hath bene done, is done agayne,</hi> for eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo is there now ſought, <hi>A nevve Reuenge for an olde Grudge.</hi> See now I praye you the practiſe and deuice of the Deuill, who, as he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes hath bene a manqueller, &amp; from the beginnyng a delighter in deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo nowe with his dromme of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance, hath he ſtricken vp a newe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum: an other fielde is pitched, the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies be armed, ye they haue hente theyr ordenaunce againſt the campe of the Chriſtians: harke, they ſhoote of, and heare ye not what a noyce theyr gunnes make? ſée howe the pellets flie through the Chriſtian campe. For who doth not behold the <hi>Papiſtes</hi> now, howe in place of the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> they warre agaynſt the <hi>Iſraelites?</hi> how haue this curſed crue, of late by heapes, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſed
<pb facs="tcp:2116:8"/> abroade thoſe deteſtable, blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous, rebellious, and contentious bookes, in the whiche is moſt manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly apparant, how they, ſettyng a parte all ſhame, neglect theyr obedience to theyr Prince, deſpiſe the truthe, and beynge voyde of the feare and grace of God, ſéeke by all meanes poſſible howe to blemiſhe and deface the inuincible veritie of our Lorde, and Sauiour Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte: whiche although by the malice of Satan, they of late did, and now againe woulde darken, yet neuer ſhalbe able to extinguiſhe &amp; put it out: yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ſe they not, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ilthely to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> out their owne ſhame, with the battery of their bookes, ſo burniſhed with blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, and ſo lewdly enterlaced with lotheſome and loude lies, as they are vtterly to be baniſhed, and not to be ſuffered in any Chriſtian Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet ſuche is their follie, and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious franſie, and their hartes ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly fretted with deadly rancour, that they nothynge regarde nor conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="tcp:2116:8"/> the Councell of the holy Ghoſte: Who ſaith, <note place="margin">VViſedo. 1.</note> 
               <hi>that the mouthe that ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth lies, ſlayeth the Soule:</hi> But rather deſpiſinge the righteouſe, <note place="margin">VViſed. 3.</note> &amp; forſakyng the Lorde, they are very ſtraglers, and ſtraiers abroade, ſhewyng themſelues as they are, euen a miſerable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of vacaboundes, and maiſterleſſe men, a careleſſe companie voyde of godly ſkil: ſouldiours of Satan, whoſe ſoules are darkened, and blinded through igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance: and whoſe malice hath ſo moul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered away their wittes, that they can not retayne nor comprehende godly wiſdome, for wante wherof, they ſeeke their owne death in the errour of their life, and deſtroye them ſelues through the wycked woorkes of their owne handes, but their gunnes are not to be feared, for theyr ordinaunce, beynge but quill gunnes, and theyr ſhotte but Paper pelllets, infected with the moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of their owne malitious mindes, dothe, euen as poyſon to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſelues, returne with rebou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des to their owne
<pb facs="tcp:2116:9"/> ſhame and confuſion. But Lord, what a ſtonie and harde harted Capitayne hath this careleſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> choſen them to be their Champion? Forſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>th euen <hi>M. Doctor Harding,</hi> who, now hath taken vppon him, in the place of <hi>Goliah,</hi> to ſtande at defiance with whole <hi>Iſraell,</hi> but ſuch men, ſuche mayſter: ſuch ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours, ſuch Capitaine: and no maruel is it that ſuche a falſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>tor be founde amongſt ſo great and noyſom a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, when amongeſt the .xij. Apoſtles one <hi>Iudas</hi> betrayed his maſter <hi>Chriſte</hi> and for a ſmall ſumme of monye, bothe ſolde &amp; deliuered him into the handes of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Prieſtes: But accordynge as it is ſayde, <note place="margin">Matth. 26.</note> 
               <hi>VVo to that man by vvhome the Sonne of man ſhalbe betrayed, for it had bene good for him that he had neuer bene borne:</hi> as the ende of his trauell well declared, who through deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hanged him ſelfe, for that he had betrayed the innocent bloudde. Lo; there beholde the rewarde of an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull ſeruant. But M. <hi>Doctor Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:2116:9"/> hath forgotten this, he hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten alſo whoſe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he him ſelf once was, he did were Chriſte his badge, he was cladde in the glitteryng garment of the glorious Goſpell, and was a me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Churche Apoſtolicall: but nowe he hath with <hi>Iudas</hi> forſaken his maiſter, and is with him become of the Churche infernall and diabolicall: for he hath refuſed and forſaken the woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie liuerie of the liuinge Lorde, and wickedly wrapped him ſelfe in the clouted cloke of the Lordes lotheſome enemie the triple crowned tyraunte, whoſe mallice againſt the truth by no meanes can be qualified, &amp; whoſe inſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiable thirſte the bloud of the ſainctes of God in defence of the ſame, can in no wiſe quenche nor ſatiſfie. But M. <hi>Doctor Hardinge</hi> beynge forgetfull of <hi>Iudas</hi> his miſerable ende is alſo as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle mindefull of his owne, yet let him take hede: <note place="margin">Sirach. 10.</note> For the ſéede whiche tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſeth the commaundementes of the Lorde ſhalbe ſhamed, for who ſhall iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie
<pb facs="tcp:2116:10"/> him that ſinneth againſt him ſelf, and who will honour him that diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noreth his owne ſoule: <note place="margin">VViſed. 2.</note> no, horrible is the death and end of the vnrighteous. But to procede, now is maſter <hi>Doctor Harding</hi> ſtirred vp by the deuice of the Deuill to ſtriue againſte the ſtreame, and in euery condition euen as <hi>Goliah</hi> was, ſo is he likewiſe armed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> toppe to toe, from the head to the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>te: for in place of an Helmet of braſſe, he hath cloſe buckled about his eares, the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy head péece of Hereſies: and in ſtéede of a cote of mayle, he hath put on the coate armour of errour, he hath han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynge about his necke the ſhielde of ſhameleſnes: and for bootes of braſſe he is laden with blaſphemie againſt the truth: and for his ſpeare he hath ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his cruell wrath: and thus beynge armed pointe deuice for his purpoſe as he thinketh, abroade he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth, before the face of Iſraell: he brauleth, he chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, he taunteth, he threateneth, he rayleth, he is at defiance with any that
<pb facs="tcp:2116:10"/> dare come: and f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ynge no perill, but makyng accompte that he hath wonne the fielde before it be foughte, he it is that will fighte in his holy Father the Popes cauſe, with him that beareth an head: but ye ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the olde prouerbe fulfilled, which is, that pryde is taken in a nette. For beholde the Lorde li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, who as he was not forgetfull of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> but deliuered them from the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> and that by the handes of <hi>Dauid</hi> his ſeruaunt: by whome that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>les <hi>Goliah</hi> was ouerthrowen: <note place="margin">Pſalm. 129.</note> So hath the Lorde done great thinges for vs: ye the Lorde hath done greate thinges for vs alredie, for euen nowe in the defence of his Churche of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glande, he hath rayſed vp an other, whome he hath appointed his inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to woorke his will by: and hath made him honorable amonge the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, a reuerent Father in God the bleſſed Biſhoppe of <hi>Saliſburie,</hi> that ioyfull <hi>Iuell</hi> of Ieſus Chriſte, to encou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this newe founde <hi>Philiſtine Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:2116:11"/> and to put him to the worſe: Oh mightie worke of God, a méeke ſprited Lambe, to conquere a ragynge Lion: the weake to ouerthrowe the ſtronge, weake I ſaye in bodie, but ſounde in ſoule: whoſe giftes in Godly know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſurmounteth, whoſe ripe vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandinge and perfectneſſe in the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers and Doctors of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue Apoſtolicall Churche, is ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and in Gods booke the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, profounde: whereof I make the whole worlde Iudge, to whome his woorthie woorkes are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted, whiche in the ſame doo ſpreade abroade his wel deſerued fame. Lo, ſuche a Champion hath the Lord of Hoſtes appointed for the defence of his Churche, who buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in harte with Gods mighte, and readie in his name to reue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the great blaſphemie of this arrogant <hi>Papiſte,</hi> marched forwarde, not with worldly pollicie, not in Armour, not with ſpeare, and ſhielde, neither highe min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, nor yet with proude lookes, but
<pb facs="tcp:2116:11"/> with a lowlie harte, and an inuincibly Faith in Ieſus Chriſte, beynge onely furniſſhed with the ſlinge of Godly zeale, wherein he puttinge the ſmooth ſtone of truthe, whiche he had choſen foorth of the brooke of Goddes bleſſed Booke, the whiche he ſlingynge at the proude arrogant Papiſticall <hi>Harding,</hi> hath therewith ouerthrowen him, and geuen him ſuch a dreadful dente in his forehead, whiche is ſo feſtered that all the filthie fraternetie of that butcher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly broode, and blouddie brotherhoode of the <hi>Babylonicall,</hi> &amp; <hi>Antechriſtian Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſtes,</hi> ſhall with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſurgerie of their Siſme, neuer be able to cure. Thus M. <hi>Doctor Harding</hi> in a piteous perplexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and as one caſte in his owne turne by beynge reproued in falcifiynge the Doctors, ſo euen as <hi>Dauid</hi> did <hi>Goliah,</hi> hath the woorthie <hi>Iuell</hi> cut of <hi>Hardinges</hi> head with his owne ſwoorde: wherfore well may we now ſaye with the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt. <note place="margin">Pſalm. 129.</note> Many a time haue thine enemies fought againſt vs (oh Lord) euen from
<pb facs="tcp:2116:12"/> our youth vp, ye many a time haue they vexed vs from our youth vp, yet haue they not preuailed againſt vs, for as the Lorde God of powre hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies, and at all times, preſerued and deliuered his chooſen <hi>Iſraell,</hi> from the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des of their enemies, ſo hath he now likewiſe ſtretched foorth his hande vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theyr furiouſnes, and hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this woorthie warriour and ine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable <hi>Iuell,</hi> to be a defence for his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who through the powre and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the euer liuyng Lorde, hath thus wounded our mortal enemie, not a man, but rather a Monſter, a Doctor by name, but a Deuill in harte, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolter from the truth, an enemie to bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and ſoule, and can any man I pray you be counted more carefull and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, then he that fighteth in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the truth of Ieſus Chriſte the onely redemer of the worlde, as this bleſſed Biſhop hath now done. Lette <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Hanyball</hi> be bruted for Warriours, <hi>Iuell</hi> in my Iudgement
<pb facs="tcp:2116:12"/> hath beſt behaued him ſelfe: wherefore if well doynge may woorthely clayme a good reporte, then geue to Gods good <hi>Iuell</hi> our comfortable captaine his wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull deſerued prayſe, for if vertue coulde ſpeake, woulde ſhe not confeſſe that <hi>Iuell</hi> had her in full poſſeſſion, and let now this queſtion be moued I pray thée: what might this cherefull cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion, this <hi>Iuell</hi> of ioye hope for, by the matchyng with, and maſtering of ſuch a monſter otherwiſe then forced tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the loue he beareth to the flocke and famelie of the faithfull, the quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the Congregation, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge to his duetie, the aduauncement of the glory of God, whoſe ſeruaunt he is, and whome he therefore hath nowe worthely ſerued, whereby he hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned and wonne vnto him ſelfe the thinge he ſought not for, the very gifte of God euen immortall fame, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let <hi>Iſraell</hi> truſte in the Lorde, from this time foorth for euer more, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this acte or ſuch other like cometh into
<pb facs="tcp:2116:13"/> our mindes: let vs remember what a great God the Lorde is, <note place="margin">VViſed. 6.</note> that thus hath weaponed his Creature, to be aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of his and our enemies, and let vs alſo prayſe God in them by whome he hath wrought ſuche wonders, to the conſtante keepinge of our profeſſion made to him in oure Baptiſme: But ſhall we thinke it now ſufficient, that <hi>Iuell</hi> hath geuen <hi>Hardinge</hi> his deadly wounde: no no, more then it was that <hi>Dauid</hi> gaue the ouerthrowe to <hi>Goliah,</hi> who beyng conquered, we Reade that the men of <hi>Iſraell</hi> &amp; <hi>Iuda:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Reg. 17.</note> aroſe, ſhouted and folowed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then after the armie of the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> which fledde: and chaſed them till they fell downe dead, and till they came to the valley, and to the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry gates of <hi>Ackaron.</hi> Alſo the like we Reade of that woorthie woman <hi>Iudith,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iudith. 15.</note> who when through the mightie aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of God ſhe had made a deuition of <hi>Holofernes</hi> head from his ſhoulders, the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> then iſſued foorth and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> with ſounde of
<pb facs="tcp:2116:13"/> Trumpettes triumphantly, and ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comforted them, and flewe them with the ſwoorde, and followed them to the vttermoſte parte of their borders.</p>
            <p>Alſo Paule fought not alone with the ſwoorde of Gods woorde, but as well the reſte of the Apoſtles, layde aboute them with the ſame weapon, vppon as many as reſiſted the veritie. But now who almoſte (but onely that woorthie <hi>Iuell</hi>) addreſſeth him ſelfe for the better eaſement and godly comfortyng of his Chriſtian bretherne? wherefore (oh ye reuerent Fathers and fellow Biſhops with <hi>Iuell,</hi> and alſo all others whome God hath made ſkilfull Souldiers in the handelinge of the weapon of his Woorde, and guides to his flocke) I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeche you ſpeake all with one voyce, be ye knitte together, be ye al of one, and the ſame minde and meaninge with <hi>Paule:</hi> prepare your ſelues to the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayle: &amp; <hi>Goliah</hi> beynge by <hi>Dauid</hi> ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne, purſue you his Souldiours with might and maine, laye about you,
<pb facs="tcp:2116:14"/> downe with them, ſtrike, lay on loade, not with materiall weapon, but with the two edged ſwoorde of the Goſpell: blow vp the trumpet of truth in Sio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that it maye ſounde ſo ſhrillie in the eares of the enemies, that they maye tremble there at and be diſcomfited: oh furniſhe Gods fortreſſes, double man them, repleniſh the pulpittes, let your tounges be talkinge, and your pennes walking, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as dartes to perce Gods and your enemies, follow them to <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen</hi> gates, whither they be fledde to hide them from the face of God, from the preſence &amp; hearynge of his woorde, and from whence they dayly ſhoote of their flaunderous ſhotte againſt you, whome God hath made to be teachers of righteouſnes, ſhepeheardes to his flocke, Capitaynes of his campe, &amp; go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours of his Congregation: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be carefull of the armie royall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to your conductinge, that when the paye daie commeth, ye maye at the handes of the Kinge eternall receiue
<pb facs="tcp:2116:14"/> the rewarde appointed for ſuche as faithfully fulfill his holie will. To whome, and to Ieſus Chriſte his true and onely Sonne, with the holy Ghoſt that ſwéete Comforter, thrée perſons and one God, be all prayſe and glorie worlde with out ende. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <l>The wicked falce reportes,</l>
                  <l>of tounges ſhall neuer ſeace:</l>
                  <l>Nor Pharaos trayne be cleane ouerthrowne,</l>
                  <l>nor Iſraell liue in peace.</l>
                  <l>Nor yet Bethulia haue iuſte cauſe</l>
                  <l>to triumphe thorowly,</l>
                  <l>Till God our Iudith moue with ſwoorde</l>
                  <l>to ſtrike for Victorie.</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <closer>
               <signed>ꝙ I. S.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
